<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trew report of the dysputacyon had [and] bego[n]ne in the conuocacyo[n] hows at london among the clargye there assembled the xviij. daye of October in the yeare of our lord M.D.LIIII.</title>
            <author>Philpot, John, 1516-1555.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849874</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15046</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09616)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15046)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 572:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trew report of the dysputacyon had [and] bego[n]ne in the conuocacyo[n] hows at london among the clargye there assembled the xviij. daye of October in the yeare of our lord M.D.LIIII.</title>
                  <author>Philpot, John, 1516-1555.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[74] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Alexander Edmonds [i.e. Jan Gheylliaert and Steven Mierdman?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Basil [i.e. Emden] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1554]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Philpot.</note>
                  <note>The imprint, from colophon, is false; actual place of publication supplied and printers' names conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁶ (-E6).</note>
                  <note>The meeting was actually held in 1553.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15046:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15046:1"/>
            <p>The trew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the dyſputacyon had &amp; bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hows at london among the clargye there aſſembled the xviij. da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye of October in the yeare of our lord M.D.LIIII.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>i. Iohan. iiij.</bibl> Proue euery ſpyryte whether thei be of god or no.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15046:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15046:2"/>
            <head>To the Chryſten reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowen to the world / Chryſten reader / what varietie and conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath bene abowt wey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghti matters of religion for a gret ſpace / which were thought to haue bene ſo diſiuſſed debated and examined of our clergie / that all men were in hope that ſuch an vniformitie agreable to the word of god / to the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine of the patriarkis and apoſtles &amp; to the order of the primatiue church al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo / had bene determined for our church of Ingland / that from henſforth one ſhuld haue liued wyth a nother in moch better vnitie and godli quietnes than in mani yeares before they had done: euery one imbracing one ſincere maner of worſhipping and inuocacion off god / wythowt any ſuperſticion / ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie or hipocriſy that hath in proceſſe of time crept in by the diuiſe and fanta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſie of mans braine. And the thing was brought to ſuch a point that all men / in maner / were wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to a wonderfull in
<pb facs="tcp:15046:3"/>
differency / and bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to eſpie their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and errors wherewyth they haue bene heretofore blynded and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, But the awncient aduerſari of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kind / Satan / which neuer ceaſeth to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke how he may deſtroye the workes of god in vs / enuieng that vnitie in trewe religion that all men of all agis ſtatis and degreys as well high as lowe / had in maner atteyned and were well nigh comne vnto / hath now ſtirred vp the old co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agayne bringing the wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke vnlerned and ſimple ſort thereby in to ſuch a dowt and wauering that they can now leſſer tell what they may bile<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue and which waye they may ſteye their faith and conſtiencys than euer thei could before. But as the great prophete (as Moyſes nameth him) the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god doth prophecy and wytnes / that offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cys muſt nedis come / and that ſuch offencys ſhuld come that euen the veri elect / (yff it were poſſible) ſhuld be ſeduced / now we ſee wyth our eyes and grope wyth our ſenſys that it is comne to paſſe and fullfilled euyn among vs. But let them take hede that haue bene
<pb facs="tcp:15046:3"/>
the auctors thereoff ffor as it ſeruyth for the prouing and tryeng of gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect (to whom all thyngs worke to the beſt) euen ſo ſhall it ſerue to theyr woo and vtter damnacion / as he ſayth that knoweth all thingis (ve homini illi per quem ſcandalum venit) woo vnto that man thorow whom offence doth come. And let the godly ſort now reioyſe in the croſſe of chriſt / for they haue no leſſe cauſe / for as moch as by this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue the ſame toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that theyr profeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the trewe religyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god / which all the trewe byleuers euermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme to time haue had / that is to ſaye / chriſtys croſſe the token that can not deceiue vs / and with owt the wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich we can not be / yff we will be ſure to liue godly in chriſt / as holy. ſ. Paul ſayth. But now to my purpoſe as in other poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tys moch varietye of opinyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hatth bene / euyn ſo in the hygh miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of chriſtys ſupꝑ (which was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord / loue and vnitie) the difference and diuerſytie of opynio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s there abowt hath brought to paſſe that more dyſcord / diſſenſion and
<pb facs="tcp:15046:4"/>
diuiſyon hath growen among men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowt that than in any other one arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our chryſten religyon. And the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refor they whos ſubſcripcyon was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred in the conuocacyon holden at powlys at the laſt parlament / iudged not amyſſe / that thought it neceſſary to reaſon and diſpute therein before they wold ſubſcrybe to any concluſyon or determynate ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that all men may knowe and ſee what reaſons and anſwers were made on both partys / I haue thought good to publyſſh ſo moch thereoff as came vnto my handis / truſting that no man wyll be more offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded wyth the ſettyng furth thereoff / to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ſuch as were not preſent may reade ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gys as there were done and ſayd / no more than they were that all that were preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhuld heare them / and iudge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyfferently by the toch ſtone of gods word / on whych part the truth doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne. Whych / men may well goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowt to ſuppreſſe / but whan they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue done all they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt it / yet will it owt and haue the ouer hand. God
<pb facs="tcp:15046:4"/>
grant that all men may ſeke and ſtudy for the truth and not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeluys to be caryed abowt nor changed with euery blaſt of ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge doctrine / nor with euery fantaſtycall fable of Antychry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtys mynyſters. Amen.</p>
            <p>And as by readyng and weyng the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and anſwers of thys dyſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I dowt not but thow ſhalt be ſuſſycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly confyrmed in the truth of the arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles therei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſoned and debated / euyn ſo in a lytle treatyſe of the trewe ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which by gods gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce ſhall ſhortly alſo be ſet furth / thow ſhalt be inſtructed what to iudge off o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther artycles / as of the maſſe / of alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys / of the inuocatyon of ſayntys / and ſuch lyke. And now that we ſee how gods wrath is bent ouer our nacyon / that we may now well ſaye wyth da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd / O god / heathen peple are ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd in to thyne inherytans. (For now Antychryſtys generacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinck to ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Ingla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for euer) let all faythfull hartis yoyne them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis together in vnfayned and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prayer that god will haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vs
<pb facs="tcp:15046:5"/>
and defend vs againſt them / that the light of his word which hath now nys ſhyned vp on vs o may both be preſerued among vs / and alſo preſerue vs agaynſt all the practiſes and enterpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of hys enemies Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15046:5"/>
            <head>The trew report of the diſputacyon had &amp; bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uocacyon hows at london the xviij. of October. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. M.D.LIIII.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas dyuers and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten rumors be ſpred abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the diſputacyon had in the conuocacyon hows / to the intent that all men may knowe the certentye of all thyngs therein done and ſayd as moch as the memory of hym that was preſent the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reat can beare a way / he hath thought good at requeſt / thoroughly to deſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be what was ſayd therein o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both parts of the matters argued and had in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyon and of the entrans thereoff.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt vp on wedynſday beyng the xviij. day off october at affter noone / maſter weſton the prolocutor certified the hows that it was the quenys plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:15046:6"/>
that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the ſame hows be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yg many lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſembled / ſhuld debate of matters of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te lawes thereoff / which hyr grace and the ꝑlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wold ratifye. And for that there is a booke of late ſet furth / called the cathechyſme (whych he ſhewed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th) beari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the name of thys honorable Synody / and yet putt furth with owt your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſentis / as I haue lerned / being a book very peſtiferos / &amp; full of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes (as he ſayd) and lyke wyſe the boo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer / very abhomynable (as it pleaſed hym to terme it) he thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght it therfor beſt fyrſt to begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth the artycles of the cathechyſme concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the ſacrament of the altar / for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrme the naturall preſens of chryſt in the ſame / and for tranſſubſtantya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. In the which on fryday next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewyng / he wylled all men there frely to ſpeak theyr tonſciens and lerning / and they ſhuld be fully ſatyſfyed.</p>
            <p>The fryday comyng beyng the xx. of October / whan men had thought they ſhuld haue ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yd diſputacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ꝓpoſed / the ꝓlocutor dyd exhyby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ij. ſeuerall billys vnto the hows: tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne for the natural <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of chryſt in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the altar / the other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:15046:6"/>
the cathechiſme / that it was not of that hows agreame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſet furth and that thei doo not agree thereunto. Requyryng all them to ſubſcrybe to the ſame as he himſylf had done: whereunto the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le hows dyd i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>medyately aſſent except vi. which were the deane of rocheſter the deane of exceter / the archdeacon of wyncheſter / the archdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hertford / the arthdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſtowe and one other / And whyle the reſt were abowt to ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcribe thes ij. articles. I. filpot ſtode vp and ſpake firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the article of the cathechyſme that he thought thei were deceyued in the tytle of the cathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiſme / in that it bearyth the title of the Synode of london laſt before this / all though mani of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent were neuer made pryuy thereof in ſetting it furth / for that this hows had gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the auctorytye to make eccleſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical lawys vnto certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſons to be appoynted by the kyngys mageſtye / and what ſoeuer eccleſyaſticall lawes thei or the moſt part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did ſet furth accordyng to a ſtatute in that behalf ꝓuyded / it might be wel ſayd to be do / ne in the ſynode of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> although ſuch as be of this hows now had no notyce thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:15046:7"/>
the ꝓmulgacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in this point he thought the ſetterfurth thereoff no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to haue ſlandred the hows / as thei by theyr ſubſcripcyon went abowt to perſuade the world / ſins thei had our ſynodall auctoritie vnto them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to make ſuch ſpirituall lawys as they thought conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and neceſſary. And more ouer he ſayd as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the naturall preſens in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament / that it was aga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yſt reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and order of lernyng and alſo very preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall to the truth that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to ſubſtribe before the matter were thorowly examined and diſcuſſed. But wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſawe that allegacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke no place / being as a man aſtoyned at the multitude of ſo mani lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as there were off purpoſe gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to mainteyne old tradicyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re than the truth of gods holy word / he made his requeſt vnto the prolocutor- that where as there were ſo many awn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſent on that ſyde as in the realme the lyke againe were not to be fownd in ſuch nomber / and that on the other ſyde of them that had not
<pb facs="tcp:15046:7"/>
ſubſcrybed / were not paſt .v. or vi. both in age and lerning farr inferyor vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / therfor that equalite might be had in this diſputacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deſyered that the prolocutor wold be a meane vnto the lordes that ſome of thos that were ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſetters furth of the ſame cathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiſme might be broght in touthe hows to ſhewe theyr lerning that mouyd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſett furth the ſame / And that D. ryd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ley and maſter rogers with ij. or iij. moo might be lycenſed to be preſent at this diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to be aſſociate with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This requeſt was thought reaſonable and was ꝓpoſed vnto the lord biſſhops who made this anſwer that it was not in them to call ſuch parſonis vnto our hows / ſyns ſome of them were priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But thei ſayd thei wold be peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yoners in this behalff vnto the cown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell / and in caſe any were abſent that ought to be of the hows / they willed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be taken in vnto them / yff they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. Affter this thei minding to haue enterid in to diſputacyon / there came a gentleman a meſſenger fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord gret maſter ſignyfieng vnto the prolo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cutor
<pb facs="tcp:15046:8"/>
that my lord gret maſter and the earle of deauonſhyre wold be preſent at the diſputacyons / and therfor he dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferryd the ſame vntill monday at one of the clock at affternone.</p>
            <p>Vp on mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day the xxiij. of October at the tyme appoynted / in the preſens of many earlys / lordis / knyghtis / gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and diuers other of the coint and of the cytye alſo / the ꝓlocutor made a ꝓteſtacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they of the hows / had appoynted thys diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / <note place="margin">weſton</note> not to call the truth in to dowt / to the which thei had allready all ſubſcribed / ſauing v. or v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. but that thos gayne ſayers myght be reſolued of theyr argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis in the whych they ſtode / as it ſhall appeare vnto yow / not dowtyng but thei wyll alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſcend vnto vs. Than he dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of maſter haddon whether he wold reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt the q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ꝓpoſed or no?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. haddon</note>To whom he made anſwere that he had certyfyed hym before by wrytyng that he wold not / ſyns the requeſt of ſuch lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as were dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be aſſyſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wold not be granted.<note place="margin">M. Elmar</note>
Maſter elmar lykewyſe was aſked / who made the prolocutor the lyke an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer / addyng moreouer thys / that they had done to moch preiudice all redy to
<pb facs="tcp:15046:8"/>
the truth / to ſubſtrybe before the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was diſcuſſed: and lytle or nothyng it myght auayle to reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the truth / ſyns all they were now determyned to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. Affter thys he dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of maſter chenye who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prolocutor ſaid allowed the preſens with them / but he denyed the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſubſtancyacyon / by the meanis of certen auctorityes vpon the which he ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth and deſyereth to be reſolued / <note place="margin">M. cheyny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s obiet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyons.</note> as yow ſhal heare whether he will ꝓpoſe hys dowtis concernyng tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or no Yea / quoth he / I wold glady mi dowtes to be reſolued which moue me not to byleue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyacion. The firſt is owt of the ſcripture of ſ. Paull to the corinthyans who ſpeaking of the ſacrament of the body and blood of chryſt calleth it offt tymis bread / affter the conſecracyon. The ſecond is owt off Orygen / who ſpeakyng of this ſacrament ſayth that the materyal part theroff goyth down to the excrementis. The third is owt of theodoretus who makyng mencyon of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall bread and wyne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecracyon ſayth that they goo not owt of their former ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / forme and ſhape. Thes be ſome of my dowtis
<pb facs="tcp:15046:9"/>
amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g many other which I require to be anſwered off. Than the prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor aſſigned D. Moreman to anſwer hym.<note place="margin">More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans aaſwer to ſ. Paul.</note> Who to. ſ. Paull anſwered hym thus / that the ſacrament is called bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ad by him in dede / but it is thus to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that it is bread off the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall bread / that is / the forme of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad.<note place="margin">Maſter cheyny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es reply<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacion.</note>
Than maſtery cheny / inferred and alleaged that hifichyus calleth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament both bread and fleſſh. Yea / quoth moreman / hyfichyus calleth it bread becaus it was bread and not by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus it is ſoo. And paſſyng ouer oryge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came to theodoretus / and ſayd that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſtoke his auctoryte / by interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a generall in to a ſpeciall / as peter martyr hath done in that place of theo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doret / <note place="margin">More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans anſwer to theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorete. marcke this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhyyfft.</note> interpreting / ouſia / for ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / which is a ſpeciall ſignyficacion of the word. whereas ouſia is a generall word as well to accyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as to ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And therfor I anſwer thus vnto Theodoret that the ſacramentall bread and wyne doo not goo owt of their former ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance forme and ſhape / that is to ſay / not owt of theyr accidentall ſubſtance
<pb facs="tcp:15046:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſhape. Affter this maſter theny ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te him down / and by and by maſter el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar ſtode vp / <note place="margin">M. elmar.</note> as one that could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde to heare ſo fond an anſwer to ſo graue an auctorite / And reaſonyd vp on the auctorite of theodoret / alleagyd before by maſter cheny and declared that moremans anſwer to theodoret was no iuſt nor ſufficyent anſwer but an illuſyon and a ſuttle euaſyon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Theodoretis meanyng. For / ſayd he / yff (ouſia) ſhuld ſignifye an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the place alleaged as it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by maſter moreman / than we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it a word ſuperfluos ſet in theodore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / there where doo folow ij. other wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis which ſufficyently do expownd the accyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the bread / that is / eidos and ſhema / which ſignifye in Inglyſh / ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and forme: And ſo very lernydly ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd owt of the ſame auctor by dyuers allegacyons that (ouſia) in greke could not be ſo generally taken in that place as moreman for a ſhyfft wold haue it.<note place="margin">more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſhifft is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</note>
But morema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a man hauyng no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſalue for that ſore affyrmed ſtyll that (ouſia) which ſignyfyeth ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / 
<pb facs="tcp:15046:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
muſt nedis ſignifye accydental ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce properly.<note place="margin">fylpots replica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / to more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſhyfft.</note> To whos importunyte ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns he could haue no nother anſwer / el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar as a man weryed wyth ſo long talk gaue place. Affter this / ſtode vp Iohn fyllpot and ſayd that he could proue that by the matter that Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret intreated off in the place aboue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged and by the ſimylytude which he makyth to proue his purpoſe / by no meanis maſter moremans interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of (ouſia) / myght be taken for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydentall ſubſtance as he for a ſhyfft wold interpret yt to be. For the matter whych theodoret intreatyth off in that place is agaynſt eutyches an heretyke which denyed ij. naturys of ſubſtance to remayne in chriſt beyng one parſon but that hys humanytye affter thac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complyſhment of the myſtery of our ſaluacyon aſcendyng in to heauyn and beyng yoyned vnto the dyuynitie was abſorpt or ſwalowed vp of the ſame / ſo that chryſt ſhuld be no more but of one dyuyne ſubſtance only by hys opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon. Agaynſt whych opynyon Theo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doret wrytyth and by the ſymylytude
<pb facs="tcp:15046:10"/>
of the ſacrament proueth the contrary agaynſt the heretyke / that lyke as in the ſacrament of the body of chriſt aff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the conſecracyo there is the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of chryſtis humanytye with the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance of bread / remaynyng as it was before / not beyng abſorpt of the huma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitye of chryſt but yoyned by the diuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne operacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereunto / Euyn ſo in the parſon of chryſt beyng now in heauyn of whom this holy ſacrament is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentacyon / there be ij. ſeuerall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancys / that is / his dyuynytye and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie vnited in one hipoſtacy or par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / which is chryſt / The humanitye not abſorpt by the coniunccyon of the deitye / but remaini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in his former ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtans. And this ſimilytude / quoth fyll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot / brought in of theodorete to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fownd Eutyches / ſhuld proue nothing at all / yff the very ſubſtance off the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall bread dyd not remayne as it dyd before / but yff D. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans interpretacion might take pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce for tranſſubſtancyacyon / than ſhuld the heretyke haue thereby a
<pb facs="tcp:15046:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtrong argument by theodoretis aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytye ſo taken to maynteyne his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy and to proue him filff a good chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man / and he might well ſaye thus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theodorete. Lyke as thow theodoret yff thow were of D. Morema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mynd / doyſt ſay that affter the conſecracyon in the ſacrament the ſubſtance of the bread is abſorpt or tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſubſtancyate in to the humane body of chryſt coming thereunto / ſo that in the ſacrament is now but one ſubſtance of the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte a lone and not the ſubſtance of bread as it was before / euyn likewyſe may I affyrme and conclude by thyne own ſimilytude that the humanitye aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendyng vp by the powr of god in to heauyn and adioyned vnto the deytye was by the might thereoff abſorpt and turned into one ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with the dey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye: ſo that now there remaynith but one diuyne ſubſtance in chriſt / nomore than in the ſacramentall ſygnis of the lordis ſupper affter the conſecracyon doo remayne any more than one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance according to your byleffe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruccyon. To this D. Moreman ſtac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered
<pb facs="tcp:15046:11"/>
in anſwering / whos defect fyll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pott perceyuing / ſpake on this wiſe.<note place="margin">more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ryh and can not tell what to anſwer. weſton is offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded.</note>
Wel maſter morema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf you hauenota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwer ready at this preſent / I pray yow diuyſe one yff you can conuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly / agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt our next metyng here aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yn: with that his ſayng the prolocutor was greuoſly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / tellyng him that he ſhuld not bragg there / but that he ſhuld be fully anſwered. Than ſayd fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot / It is the thing that I only deſyre to be anſwered directly in this behalff / and I deſyre of yow &amp; of all the hows at this preſent / that I may be ſufficye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered / which I am ſure yow are not all able to doo / ſaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theodoretis autorite and ſimilytude vpright / as he ougt to be taken. No nother anſwer was made to fillpots reaſons / but that he was commanded to ſylens.<note place="margin">Fylpot, tis repli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vp the deane of rocheſter offring hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſylff / to reaſon in the fyrſt queſtion aga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynſt the natural preſens wiſſhing that the ſcripture and the awncyent doctors in this point might be weyed / byleuid and folowed. And agaynſt this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall preſens he thought the ſayng of
<pb facs="tcp:15046:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
chryſt in. ſ. Mathew to make ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ynough / yff men wold credite and fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe ſcripture: who ſayd there of him ſelff that poore men we ſhuld haue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weis with vs / <note place="margin">the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> but him we ſhuld not ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue alweys / which was ſpoken / quoth he / concerning the naturall preſens of chriſtis body / therfor we ought to byle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue as he hath taught that chriſt is not naturally preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t on earth in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the altare.<note place="margin">weſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s anſwer to the deane.</note> To this was anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red by the prolocutor that we ſhuld not haue chryſt preſent allweyes to exercy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe almes dedis vp on hym / but vp on the pore. But the deane proſecuted his argument / and ſhewed owt of. ſ. Auſten further / that the ſame interpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyon of the ſcripture alleaged / <note place="margin">The dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> was no ſufficyent anſwer / who wrytych in the fyfftye treatiſe of ſ. Iohan on thys wyſe of the ſame ſentence. Whan as he ſayd / ſayth Auſten / me ſhall ye not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue allweyes with you / he ſpake of the preſence of his body. For by his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtye / bi his prouydence / by hys vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable
<pb facs="tcp:15046:12"/>
and vyſyble grace / that is fullfylled which is ſayd of him / behold I am with yow vntyll the conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the world.<note place="margin">A nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritye owt of. ſ. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> But in the fleſſh which the wore toke vp on him / in that which was borne of the virgyn / in that which was apprehended of the Iewys which was crucifyed on the croſſe / which was lett down from the croſſe / which was wrapped in clowtis / which was hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſepulchre / which was manifeſted in the reſurreccyon / yow ſhall not haue me allweyes with yow. And why? For affter a bodily preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce he was conuerſant wih his diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples xl. eayes / and thei accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeng him by ſeyng and not by folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing / he aſcendyd and is not here / for there he ſytteth at the ryght hand of the father / And yet here he is / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus he is not departed in the preſens of his mageſtye. Affter a nother ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we haue chryſt allweys by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens of hys mageſtye / but affter the <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſens off his fleſſh it is vprightly ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:15046:13"/>
you ſhall not verily haue me allweys with yow. For the church had hym in the preſence of his fleſſh a fewe dayes / and now by fayth it apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth him and ſeyth him not with eyes.<note place="margin">watſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s anſwer to ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten.</note> To this auctorite D. Watſon toke vp on him to anſwer / and ſayd he wold anſwer. ſ. Auſten by. ſ. Auſten / and hauing a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten boke in his hand of notis / he allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged owt of the xc. treatye vp on.<note place="margin">Fylpot agaynſt watſon.</note> ſ. Ioan that affter that mortall condicyon and maner we haue not now chryſt on the earth as he was heretofore before his paſſion. Agaynſt whos anſwer Iohan fillpott replyed and ſayd that watſon had not fully anſweryd. ſ. Auſten by. ſ. Auſten as he wold ſeme to haue done / for that in the place aboue mencionyd by maſter deane of rocheſter / he doth not only teach the immortall ſtate of chriſtis bodye before his paſſion / but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo the immortall condicyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame affter his reſurrection / in the which mortall body. ſ: Auſten ſemyth playne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to affirme that chriſt is not preſent-vp on the arth neyther in forme viſibly neyther in corporall ſubſtance inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly:
<pb facs="tcp:15046:13"/>
As in fewe linis affter the place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue alleaged. ſ. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth more plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely declare by thes wordis / ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / now thes ij. maner af chriſtis preſence decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red / which is by his mageſtie / prouiden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / and grace now preſent in the world which before his aſcenſyon was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in fleſſh / being now placed at the ryght hand of the father is abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the ſame from the world / I thynk / (ſayth. ſ. Auſten) that there remaynith no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this mater. Now / quoth fillpot / yff. ſ. Auſten acknowleged no more preſence of chriſt to be now on earth but only his diuyne preſence / and towching his humanitye to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyn / we ought to confeſſe and byleue the ſame. But yff we put a thyrd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens of chriſt / that is corporally to be <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent allweys in the ſacrament of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare inuiſibly / according to your ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſycions / whereoff. ſ. Auſten maketh no mencyon at all in all his workis / yow ſhall ſeme to iudge that which. ſ. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd neuer comprehend. Why / quoth watſon. ſ. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the place by me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged maketh no mencion how. ſ. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyn
<pb facs="tcp:15046:14"/>
beyng in this world ſawe Chriſt affter his aſcenſion. It is trewe / ſayd fyllpot / but he ſawe chriſt as the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture telleth / in the heauyns beyng ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſtanding at the right hand of god the father. Further to this / watſon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not.<note place="margin">D. we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton.</note> Than the prolocutor went abowt to furnyſſh vp an anſwer to. ſ. Auſten / ſayng that he is not now in the world affter that maner of bodyly preſence / but yet preſent for all that in his bodye. To whom fyllpot anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the prolocutor dyd grate moch vp on this word / (ſecundum) in. ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten / which ſignifyeth affter the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / in forme / but he doth not anſwer to / (id quod) which is that thing or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of chryſt in the which chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered / aroſe / and aſcended in to heauyn In the which thyng and ſubſtance he is in heauin and not on earth / as. ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten in the place ſpecyfyed moſt clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth defyne.<note place="margin">The dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> To this nothyng els being anſwered / maſter deane of roche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter procedid in the maintenance of his argument and redd owt of a boke of
<pb facs="tcp:15046:14"/>
annotacions / ſondry auctoryties for the confirmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereoff.<note place="margin">more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> To the which mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reman / who was appointed to anſwer him / made no direct anſwer / but bad hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make an argument / ſayng maſter dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne had recyted many wordis of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors but he made not one argument. Than ſayd maſter deane / the auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the doctors by me reherſed / be ſufficient argumentis to proue myne inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / to the which my deſire is to be an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſweryd of yow. But ſtill moreman cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed / make an argument / to ſhifft off the auctorite which he could not anſwer vnto. Affter this maſter deane made this argument owt of the inſtitucyon of the ſacrament / (Doo thys in remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance of me / and thus ye ſhal ſhewe furth the lordis death vntyll he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myth) The ſacrament therfor is the remembrance of chriſt / than it is not very chriſt for yet he is not comme. For this word / (Vntyll he comyth) doth playnely ſignifie the abſens of chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis body.<note place="margin">weſton.</note> Than the prolocutor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nt abowt to ſhewe that thys word / 
<pb facs="tcp:15046:15"/>
(Vntil he comyth / ) dyd not import any abſence of chriſt on the earth / by other placis of ſcripture where (donec) vntill / was placed as well as there / but direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly to the purpoſe he anſwered nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. In concluſyon maſter deane fel to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyoning of moreman whether chryſt ate the paſthalawb with his diſcyples or no? He anſwered / yea. Further he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded whether he ate lykewiſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament with them as he dyd inſtytute yt? Moreman anſwered Yea. Than he axed what he ate / and whether he ate his own naturall body as they ymagy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne it to be / or noo. Than ſayd maſter deane It is a great abſurdytye by yow granted / and ſo he ſate down.<note place="margin">more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth that chriſt ato his own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> Agaynſt this abſurditye / filpot ſtode vp and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued / ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he could proue by good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be diducyd owt of ſcripture / that chryſt ate not his own naturall bodye at the inſtitucyon of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / and the reaſon is this. The body of chriſt giuyn by the ſacrament hath a promes of remiſſyon of ſynnis adyoyned / vnto all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that receyue it dewely / <note place="margin">Fylpot.</note> but this promes could take no effect in chryſt / 
<pb facs="tcp:15046:15"/>
ergo chriſt ate not his own body in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.<note place="margin">more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue a ꝓmes of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of ſinne an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nexed vnto it.</note> To this reaſon morema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered / denienh the former part of the argument / that the ſacrament had a promes of remiſſyo of ſynnis annexed vnto yt. Than fillpot ſhewed this to be the promes in the ſacrament (Which is gyuyn for yow / which is ſhed for yow for the remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnis) But more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man wold not acknowlege that to be any promes / ſo that he droue fyllpot to the vi. of Ioh. to vouch his ſayng with thes wordis the breade which I will gyue / is my fleſſh / which I wyll gyue for the lyffe off the world. Moreman anſwering nothing directly to this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument / <note place="margin">harpſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reman his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed.</note> harpſfeld ſtart vp to ſupplie that which wanted in his behalff / and thinkyng to haue anſwered fyllpott / confyrmed more ſtrongly his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / ſayng / ye miſtake the promes which is annexed to the body of chryſt in the ſacrament / for it perteyned not to chriſt but to his diſcyples to whom chriſt ſayd this is my body which is gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for yow / and not for chriſt him ſylff. Yow haue ſayd well for me quoth fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pott
<pb facs="tcp:15046:16"/>
/ for that is mine argument. The promes off the body of chriſt toke no effect in chriſt / ergo chriſt ate not his own body.<note place="margin">weſton alſo is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to more man.</note> Than the prolocutor to ſhowlder owt the matter / ſayd the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument was naught / for by the like ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument he myght goo abowt to proue that chryſt was not baptyſed / becaus che remiſſyon of ſynn which is anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed vnto baptyſme toke no effect in chriſt.<note place="margin">fylpots argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not ſolu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted.</note> To the which / fyllpot replyed that lyke as chriſt was baptyſed / ſo he ate the ſacrament / but he toke on hym baptiſme / not that he had any nede the reoff / or that it toke any effect in him / but as our maſter / to gyue the church an example to folowe him in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtracyon of the ſacrament / and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to exhibite vnto vs / him ſelf / and not to giue him ſelf to him ſelff. No mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was ſayd in this. But afterward the ꝓlocutor dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of filpot / whether he wold argue agaynſt the naturall pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence or no. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he anſweared / yea yff he wold heare his argument with owt interrupcyon and aſſigne one to anſwer him and not many / which is a
<pb facs="tcp:15046:16"/>
confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the opponent and ſpecyally for him that was of an yll memori. By this tyme the night was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne on / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore the prolocutor brake vp the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putacyon for that tyme and appointed fillpot to be the fyrſt that ſhuld beginn the diſputacion the next day affter / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the preſence of chryſt in the ſacrament.</p>
            <p>On the wedinſday the xxv. of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber / Iohnnfillpott / <note place="margin">Filpot.</note> as it was before ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed / was redy to haue entred the diſputacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myndyng fyrſt to haue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a certen oracyon and a trewe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in laten off the mater of chriſtis preſens which was than in queſtyon which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the prolocutor perceyuing / by and by he forbad fillpot to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny oracyon or declaracyon of any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandyng hym alſo that he ſhuld make na argument in laten but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude no his argumentis in Inglyſſh. Than ſayd fyllpott / this is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to your order taken at the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of this diſputacyon: For than yow appoynted that all the argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſhuld be made in laten. And
<pb facs="tcp:15046:17"/>
thereupon I haue drawen and diuyſed all my argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis in laten. And becaus yow / maſter prolocutor / haue ſayd here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore openly in this hows that I had no lerning / I had thought to haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed ſuch lerning as I haue / in a brefe oracyon and ſhort declaracyon of the queſtyons now in controuerſy: thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng it ſo moſt conuenient alſo / that in caſe I ſhuld ſpeak otherwyſe in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claracyon than ſhuld ſtand with lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or than I were able to warant and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyfye by gods word / it myght the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be reformyd by ſuch as were lerned of the hows / ſo that the vnlerned ſort beyng preſent myght take the leſſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence thereat. But this allegacyon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled nothyng with the prolocutor who bad him ſtyll forme an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Inglyſſh or els to hold his peace.</p>
            <p>Than ſayd fyllpot. Yow haue ſore dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſapoynted me thus ſodenly to goo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your former order / but I wyll accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſh your commandement leauyng myne oracyon a part And I wyll co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to my argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis / the which as wel as ſo ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a warnyng wyll ſerue I wil
<pb facs="tcp:15046:17"/>
make in Inglyſſh. But before I bryng furth any argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I will in one word declare what maner of preſens I doo dyſallowe in the ſacrament to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the hearers may the better vnderſtand to what end and effect myne argumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis ſhall tende: not to denye vtterly the preſence of chriſt in hys ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wely miniſtryd accordyng to his inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucyon / but only to denye that groſſe and carnall preſens which yow of this hows haue allredy ſubſtrybed vnto to be in the ſacrament of the altar contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to the truth and manyfeſt meanyng of the ſcrypturys / That by tranſſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyacyon of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall breade and wyne chriſtis naturall body ſhuld by the vertu of the wordis pronownced by the pryſt be conteyned and included vnder the formis or accydentys of brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and wyne. Thys kynd of preſens y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magyned by men / I doo denye / quoth fyllpot / And agaynſt thys I wyll rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: But before he could make an end of that he wold haue ſayd he was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted of the prolocutor / and comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to his argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. At whos
<pb facs="tcp:15046:18"/>
vniuſt importunite fyllpot beyng offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and thincking to purchaſe hym a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy therfor / he fell down vp on his kneys before the earles and lords wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ych were there preſent / beyng a gret nomber / wherof ſome were of the que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis cowncell / beſeching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght haue libertie to proſecute his argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentis with owt interrupcyon of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the which was ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilly gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted hym of the lordis. But the ꝓlocutor putti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in vre a point of the practyſe of prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis / wold not condeſcend thereunto / but ſtyll cryed hold your peace or els make a ſhort argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. I am abowt it / quoth fyllpot / yff yow wold lett me alone. But fyrſt I muſt nedis axe a queſtion of my reſpondent (who was. D. ched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey) concernyng a word or twayne of your ſuppoſycion / that is / of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the altare / what he meanyth thereby / and whether he take as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the awncyent wryters doo / ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng the lordis ſupper the ſacrament of the altar / becaus it is a ſacrament of that liuely ſacrifyce which chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for our ſynnis vp on the altar of
<pb facs="tcp:15046:18"/>
the croſſe and becaus that chryſtis body crucifyed for vs was that blody ſacrifyee / which the blood ſhedyng of all the beaſtis offered vp on the altare in the old lawe dyd prefigurate and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie vnto vs. And in ſignifycacyon thereoff / the old writers ſometime doo call the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body and blood of chryſt / among other namis which thei aſtrybe thereunto / the ſacrament of the altare and that ryght well. But yff yow take it other wyſe / as for the ſacrament of the altare which now a dayes is made of lime and ſtone and hangen ouer the ſame / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be all one with the ſacrament of the maſſe / as it is at this preſent in many placis / <note place="margin">chedſcy</note> than I wyll direct myne argumentis accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as your anſwer ſhall gyue me oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſyon. Than made D. chedſey this an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwer that in theyr ſuppoſicyon thei to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the ſacrament of the altar and the ſacrament of the maſſe to be all one.<note place="margin">Fillpot ſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſſh.</note>
Than quoth fyllpott / I wyl ſpeake playne Inglyſſh / as Maſter prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor wylleth me / and make a ſhort reſolucyon therof / that that ſacrament
<pb facs="tcp:15046:19"/>
of the altare which ye reken to be all one with the maſſe / onys iuſtly aboliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and now put in full vſe agayne / is no ſacrament at all / neyther is chriſt in any wiſe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in yt: And this his ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he offered to proue before the hole ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ws / yff they lyſted to call him thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to / and lykewyſe offered to vouch the ſame before the quenis grace and hyr moſt honorable cowncell / before the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of vi. of the beſt lernyd men of the hows of the contrary opinyon / he refu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed none. And yff I ſhall not be able / quoth he / to mainteyne by gods word that I haue ſayd / and confownd thos vi. which ſhall take vp on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to with ſtand me in this point / let me be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with as many fagots as be in lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don / before the court gates. This he vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered with a gret vehemency of ſpirite. At this / the prolocutor with diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / were very moch offended / dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of him whether he wyſt what he ſaid or no. Yea / quoth fyllpott I wote well what I ſay: defieryng no mann to be offended with his ſayng / for that he ſpake no more than by gods word he
<pb facs="tcp:15046:19"/>
was able to proue. And praiſed be god quoth he / that the quenis grace hath gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vs off this hows (as our prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor hath informed vs) that we may frely vtter our conſciences in thes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of controuerſie in religyon.<note place="margin">Here weſton confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth fyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pot mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtilie.</note> And therfor I will ſpeake here my conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s frely / grownded vp on gods holy word for the truth: Albeyt ſome off yow he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re preſent miſlyke the ſame. Than dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the hows beſydys the prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor / tawnted and reprehended hym / for ſpeakyng ſo vnfaryngly agaynſt the ſacrament of the maſſe / And the prolo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cutor ſayd he was mad and threatened him / that he wold ſend hym to priſon yff he wold not ceaſe his ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>Than fylpot ſeing him ſelff thus abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / and not permitted with free lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to declare his mynd / fell in to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamacyon / caſtyng his eyes vp towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis the heauyn and ſaid / O lord what a world is this / O lord what meaneth this world / that the truth of thy holy word may not be ſpoken and abidden by? And for very ſorow and heuynes the tearis trykled owt of his eyes. Aff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:15046:20"/>
this / the prolocutor being mouth by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that wore abowt him / was content that he ſhuld make an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo that he wold be viefe therein.<note place="margin">Fillpot</note> I will be as brefe / quoth filpot / as I mai co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tli be in vttri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all that I haue to ſaie. And fyrſt I wil beginn to grownd mine ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentis vp on the auctorities of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures / where vp on all the bylding of our faith ought to be grownded. And affter I ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme the ſame by aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient doctores of the church. And I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my firſt argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t owt of the xxiiij. of Mathew of the ſayng of the angell to the iij. Maryes ſeking chriſt at the ſepulchre ſaing / he is riſen / he is not here: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in. ſ. luke in the xxiij. chap. the angell aſketh them / whi thei ſought him that liueth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the dead? Like wiſe the ſcripture teſtifieth that chriſt is ryſen / aſcended in to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſitteth on the right hand of the father: all the which is ſpoken of his naturall body / ergo it is not on earth included in the ſacrament. I wyll confyrme this yet moie effectually by the ſaing of
<pb facs="tcp:15046:20"/>
chryſt in the xvi. of. ſ. Iohn. I came ſaith chriſt / from my father in to the world / and now I leaue the world and goo a way to my father. The which coming / and going / he ment of his naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / therefor we may affirme thereby that it is not now in the world. But I looke here / quoth he / to be anſwered with a bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diſtinction of viſibly and inuiſibly / that he is viſibly departed in his humanite / but inuiſibly he remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not withſtonding in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but that anſwer I proue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t my ſylff that with more expedicyon I may deſcend to the pyth of myne argumentes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of I haue a doſen to propoſe / and wyll proue that no ſuch diſtinccyon maye ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke awaye the force of that argument / by the anſwer which his diſciples gaue vnto chriſt ſpeaking thes wordes / now thow ſpeakyſt plainely and vtteryſt furth no prouerbe: which wordis. ſ. cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll interpreting fayth that chriſt ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with owt any maner of impedy of obſcure ſpeach / And therefor I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude hereby / thus: that yff chryſt ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke plainely and with owt parable / (as
<pb facs="tcp:15046:21"/>
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay) ſaing / I leaue / the world now / and goo a waye to my father / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that obſcure / darke and imperceptyble pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens of chriſtes natural body to remay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in the ſacrament vp on earth inuyſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly contrary to the playne wordis of chryſt / ought not to be allowed: For nothyng can be ſayd more vncerten / or more parabolycall and vnſenſyble tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to ſaye. Here now wyll I atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what ye will anſwer / and ſo deſcend to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrmacyon of all that I haue ſayd by awncyent writers.<note place="margin">thed ſeys an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to fyllpot.</note> Than D. ched ſey recityng his argument in ſuch order as it was made / made a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer ſeuaerlly to euery part thereoff / on this wiſe Firſt to the ſaing of the angell / that chriſt is not here / And why ſeke ye the liuyng among the deade / he anſwered that thes ſayngis perteined nothyng to the preſens of chriſtes natural body in the ſacrament / but that thei were ſpoken of chriſtes body being in the ſepulchre whan the iij. maryes thought hym to haue bene in the graue ſtil. And ther for the angell ſayd / why doo ye ſeke him that liuyth among the dead. And
<pb facs="tcp:15046:21"/>
to the auctorite of the xvi-of Iohn whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re chriſt ſayth / Now I leaue the world and goo to my father / he ment that of his aſcenſyon / and ſo lykewyſe dyd ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryl / interpreting the ſaing of the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that knewe playnely that chriſt wold viſibly aſcend in to heauyn / but that yet doth not exclude his inuiſible preſens of his naturall body in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. For ſ. Chryſoſtome writing to the peple of Antioch doth affirme the ſame / comparing Helyas and chriſt to gether / and helias clooke vnto Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtis fleſſh. Helias / quoth he / whan he was taken vp in the fiery charet / lefft his clooke behind him vnto his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple helyſeus / But chriſt aſcendyng in to heauyn toke his fleſſh with him / and lefft alſo his fleſſh behynd him. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may ryght well gather that chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtis fleſſh is viſibly aſtended in to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and inuiſibly abydeth ſtill in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the altare.<note place="margin">fyllpot replied.</note> To this anſwer / fyllpot replyed / and ſayd that he infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not his argument vp on the ſayng of the angell / (Chriſt is ryſen and is not here) / but toke his beginnyng the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby
<pb facs="tcp:15046:22"/>
to ꝓcede as before is reherſed: to the ꝓces wherof yow haue not thoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wli anſwered / for I procedyd further / as thus / he is ryſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſitteth at the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of god the father ergo he is not remaining on the earth. Neither is your a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer to ciryl / by me alleaged / ſufficient: but by and by I will returne to your interpretacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of cyryll and mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re playnely declare the ſame / affter th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at I haue firſt refelled the auctorite of chryſoſtom which is one of your chefe principles that yow alledge to make for your groſſe carnall preſens in the ſacrament / the which being well weyd and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perteineth nothing the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reunto. At that the prolocutor ſtarcled that one of the chefe pillers in this po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhuld be ouertrhowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and therfor recy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſayd auctoritie in laten firſt / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d affter ward Ingliſſhed theſame / willi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all that were preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to note that ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of chriſoſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which he thought inuincible on theyr ſyde. But I ſhall make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare / quoth fylpot / by and by to make lytle for your purpos. And as he was abowt to declare his mynd in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halff
<pb facs="tcp:15046:22"/>
/ the prolocutor did interrupt him as he dyd allmoſt continually / where with fyllpot not beyng content / ſayd / <note place="margin">Fillpot is intee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted.</note> maſter prolocutor thinketh that he is in a ſophiſtrye ſcole where he knoweth right well the maner is that whan the reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent ꝑceiueth that he is like to be inforced with an argument to the wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich he is not able to anſwer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth what he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with cauyllacyon and inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dryue him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame. This ſayng of fylpot was yll lyked of the ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutor and his adherentis: and the ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutor ſayd that fillpot could bryng nothing to auoide that autorite but his own vayne ymaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Heare / quoth fyllpot / and affterward iudge. For I wyll doo in this as in all other aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes yow ſhall charge me with in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellyng any of my argumentis that I haue to proſecute anſwering eyther vnto the ſame bi ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t auctorities of ſcripture / or els by ſome other teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni of like auctoritie / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not of mine own ymaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the which yff I doo / I wil it to be of no credyte. And concernyng the ſayng of chryſoſtom / I haue ij. wayes to beate hym from your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:15046:23"/>
/ the one owt of ſcripture / the other owt of chriſoſtome him ſelff in the place here by yow alleaged. Firſt where he ſemeth to ſaye that chriſt aſcending / to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke his fleſſh with him / and lefft alſo his fleſſh behind him / truth it is: for we all doo confeſſe and byleue that chriſt toke on him our humane nature in the virgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maryes wombe / and thorow his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the ſame hath vnyted vs to his fleſſh / and thereby are we beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne one fleſſh with him / ſo that chryſoſtom mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght therefor ryght well ſaye / that chriſt aſcending toke his fleſſh which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuid of the virgine mary / a way with him: And alſo lefft his fleſh behind him / which are we / that be his elect in this world / which are the membres of chriſt / and fleſſh of his fleſſh: as very aptli. ſ. Paul to the epheſians in the iiij. chapter doth teſtifye ſayng we are fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh of chriſtes fleſſh and bones of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis / And yf percaſe any man will affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that he intreateth there of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment ſo that this interpretacyon ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſo aptly be applyed vnto hym in that place / than wyll I yet interprete chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom
<pb facs="tcp:15046:23"/>
a nother way by him ſylff. For in that place in fewe lynes before thoo words which were here no rather redd are thes wordes red / that chriſt affter he aſcended in to heauyn lefft vnto vs indewed with his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis / his fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh in miſteryes / that is ſacramentally. And that miſtycall fleſſh / chriſt leaueth as well to his church in the ſacrament of baptiſme as in the ſacramentall bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade and wyne. And that. ſ. Paul iuſtly doth wytnes / ſaing / as many of vs as are baptyſed in chriſt haue put vp on vs Chryſt. And thus yow may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that ſ. chryſoſtome maketh noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for your carnall and groſſe preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in the ſacrament as yow wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take hym.<note place="margin">Pye a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d weſton rownd to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Now in thys meane whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le maſter pye rownded the prolocutor in the eare to put fyllpot to ſilence and to appoynt ſome other / myſtruſtyng leſt he wold ſhrowdly ſhake their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preſence in concluſyon / yff he held on long / ſeing in the beginnyng he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue one of theyr chefe fowndacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſuch a pluck.<note place="margin">weſton.</note> Than the prolocutor ſayd to fyllpot / that he had reaſoned ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly
<pb facs="tcp:15046:24"/>
inough / and that ſome other ſhuld now ſupplye his romth. Where with he was not well content / ſaing / whi ſyr I haue a duſſen argumentes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter to be propoſed and I haue not yet ſearſe ouergone my fyrſt argument / for I haue not brought in any confirmacyon thereof owt of any awncyent wryter / whereoff I haue for the ſame purpoſe many / being hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtill letted by your offt interrupting of me.<note place="margin">Fillpot is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce note th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is geare</note> Well / quoth the prolocutor / yow ſhall ſpeake no more now and I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yow to hold your peace. Yow per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue / quoth fyllpot / that I haue ſtuff ynough for yow / and am able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand your fals ſuppoſicyon and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for yow co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand me to ſilence.<note place="margin">Fillpot is threa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tened to priſon. A good ſolucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for all his argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mences</note> Iff yow will not gyue place / ꝙ the ꝓlocutor / I will ſend yow to pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is not / ꝙ fyllpot / according to your ꝓmes made in this hows / nor yet accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to your bragg made at pawlys croſſe that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be anſwered in this diſputacion to what ſo euer they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay / Syns yow wyll not ſuffer me of a duſſen argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis to ꝓſecute one. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> M. pie toke vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on him to ꝓmes that he ſhuld be a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:15046:24"/>
a nother daie. Filpot ſeyng he mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ht not ꝓcede on his purpos bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g there with iuſtli offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nded: ſaing thus: a fight of yow here / which heiherto haue lurked in corners and diſſembled with god a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the world / are now gathered to gether to ſuppres the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cere truth of go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ds holy word / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſet furth eueri falſe de which by the catholike doctrine of the ſcripture / ye are not able to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne.<note place="margin">M. elmar.</note>
Than ſtepped furth maſter el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer chaplin to the duke of ſuffolk wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om maſter moreman toke vp on him to anſwer / agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt whom maſter elmer obyected diuers and ſondry auctory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes / for the confyrmyng of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he toke the day before in hand to proue that (ouſia) in the ſentence of Theodorete brought in by maſter chey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny / muſt nedes ſignifie ſubſtance and not accidence / whos lerned reaſons and clerkly approbacions becaus thei were all grownded and brought owt of the greke / I doo paſſe them ouer for that they want theyr grace in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſſh / And alſo theyr propre vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtondyng. But his allegacyons ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combred maſter morema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he deſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd
<pb facs="tcp:15046:25"/>
a day to ouer vewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for at that inſtant he was with owt a conuenient anſwer.<note place="margin">more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiereth a daye to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me craf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty ſhift.</note> Than dyd the prolocutor call maſter haddo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deane of exceter and chaplyn to the duke of ſuff. who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted theodoretis auctoritie in confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng maſter elmers argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> D. watſon toke vp on him to giue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer / who affter long talk was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fownded that he was not able to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer to a certen word (Miſterium / <note place="margin">watſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fown<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by. M. haddon</note>) but for as moch as he ſemed to dowt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in / maſter haddon toke owt of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom a latyne aucthor to confirm his ſaing / and ſhewed the ſame to maſter watſon / asking hym whether he thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght the tranſlacyon to be trewe or that the prynter were in any fawt.<note place="margin">watſon for a ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fft put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a fawt in the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</note> There may be a fawt in the pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter / quoth wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / for I am not rememberyd of this word. Than dyd maſter haddon take owt of his boſome a greke boke / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein he ſhewed furth with his fyngar the ſame wordes which maſter watſon could not denye. His argumentis fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I omyt to declare at large becaus thei were for the moſt part in greke
<pb facs="tcp:15046:25"/>
abowt the bulting owt of the trewe ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nificacyon of (ouſia). Than ſtept furth maſter perne and in argument / <note place="margin">M. perne.</note> made declaracyon of his mind againſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanciacyon and confirmed the ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gs and auctorityes alledged by maſter elmer and maſter haddon: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prolocutor a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered / ſaing I moch mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell / maſter perne / that yow will ſay thus / for ſo moch as on friday laſt yow ſubſtribed to the contrary. Which his ſaing / maſter elmer did miſlyke / ſaing to the prolocutor that he was to blame ſo to reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / partly for that thys hows / quod he / is an hows of free libertye for euery mann to ſpeake his conſcyens / <note place="margin">weſton praiſeth theyr lerning to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they but he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not ther ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> and partly for that yow pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed yeſterday that not withſtonding any man had ſubſtrybed / yet he ſhulde haue free libertie to ſpeake his mind. And for that the nyght did approch and the time was ſpent / the prolocutor gyuing them prayſes for their lerning dyd yet not with ſtondyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that all reaſoni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſett a part / the order of the holy rhurch muſt be receiuid a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges muſt be ordered thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15046:26"/>On Fryday the xxvii. of october / D. weſton the prolocutor dyd firſt propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wnd the matter ſhewyng that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon had ſpent ij. dayes in diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allreadi abowt one onely Doctor / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch was theodorete / and abowt one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word which was (ouſia.) Yet were thei comne the thyrd day to anſwer all thinges that could be obiected / ſo that thei wold ſhortly put owt theyr argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.<note place="margin">M. haddon and watſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
So maſter haddon deane of ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceter / deſiered leaue to appoſe maſter watſon / which with ij. other moo that is morgane and harpſfeld / was appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to anſwere. Maſter haddon deman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded this of him / whether any ſubſtance of breade or wyne dyd remayne affter the conſecracyon: Than maſter watſon aſked of him agayne / whether he thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght there to be a reall preſens of gods body or no? Maſter haddo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd it was not mete nor orderlyke / that he which was appointed reſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ſhuld be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent: and he whos dutye was to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yect / ſhuld anſwer. Yet maſter watſon a long while wold not agree to anſwer but that thing firſt granted hym. At
<pb facs="tcp:15046:26"/>
laſt an order was ſett / and maſter had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don had leaue to goo forward with his argument. Than he proued by theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retes wordes / a ſubſtance of breade and wine to remaine. For thes are his wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis / the ſame thei were before the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificacyon / thei are after. Maſter wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / ſaid that theodorete ment not the ſame ſubſtance but the ſame eſſence / whereupon thei were dryuen agayne vnto the diſcuſſyng of the greke word (ouſia) and maſter haddon proued it to meane a ſubſtance / both by the etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the word and by the wordis of the doctor. Firſt / quoth he / it cometh of the participle / (on / ) which deſcendeth of the verbe / ſum. And ſo the nowne (ouſia). Than maſter watſon anſwered that it had not that ſignificacyon only. Than maſter haddon prouyd that it muſt medes ſo ſignifie in that place and he axed / whan the bread and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne became ſymbolys: whereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was made / affter the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and not before. Than gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red maſter haddon this reaſon / 
<pb facs="tcp:15046:27"/>
owt of his auctor: The ſame thing / ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th theodorete / that the breade and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne were before they were ſymbolys / the ſame thei remaine ſtil in nature a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſubſtance / affter they are ſſymbolys: breade and wine they were before / the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>refor breade and wyne they are affter Than maſter watſon fell to the deniall off the auctor and ſayd he was a neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryan:<note place="margin">watſon is driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mefull ſhifft to denie the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor / wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an he can not anſwer</note>
And he deſiered that he myght anſwer ts maſter cheyny / which ſtode by / for that he was more mete to diſpu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in the matter / becaus he had gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſubſtrybed vnto the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens. Maſter cheyny deſiered pacience of the honorable me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to heare him tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting that he ſhuld ſo open the matter that the veryte ſhuld appeare: ꝓteſting furthermore / that he was no obſtyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te nor ſtubburne man / but wold be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to all reaſon.<note place="margin">M. cheyny.</note> And yff thei by theyr lernyng / which he acknowlegyd to be moch more than hys / could an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his reaſons / that than he wold be rulyd by them and ſaye as they ſayd / for he wold be no auctor of ſchiſme nor hold any thyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the holy mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:15046:27"/>
the church which is chriſtis ſpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. D. Weſton liked this well and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him highly / ſaing that he was a well lerned man / and a ſober ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and well execuſed in all good lerning and in the doctors / and finalli a man mete / for hys knowlege / to diſpute in that place / I pray yow heare hym / quoth he Than maſter cheyny deſyeryd ſuch as there were preſent to pray ij.<note place="margin">M. chenys prayer.</note> wordys with hym vnto god / and to ſay (vincat veritas) let the veryte take place and ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the vyctory. And all that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent cryed with a lowd voyce / vincat veritas / vincat veritas. Than ſayd doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor weſton to him / that was hipocryti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. Men may better ſay / quoth he / vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cit veritas / Truth hath goten the victo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. Maſter cheyny ſayd agayne yff he wold gyue him leaue he wold bryng it to that point that he myght well ſay ſoo.<note place="margin">M. cheny and wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon.</note> Than he diſputed with maſter wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon affter this ſort / yow ſayd that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter haddon was vnmete to diſpute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus he granteth not the naturall and reall preſens / but I ſape yow are moch more vnmete to anſwer / becaus yow
<pb facs="tcp:15046:28"/>
take a way the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Maſter watſon ſaid he had ſubſtribed to the reall preſens and ſhuld not goo a waye from that. So ſayd weſton alſo and the reſt of the priſtis / in ſo moch that off a gret while he could haue no leaue to ſay any more / till the lordis ſpake and willed that he ſhuld be hard. Than he told them what he ment by his ſubſcribing to the reall preſence / farr other wiſe than they ſuppoſed: ſo than he went forward and proſecuted maſter haddons argument in prouing that (ouſia) was a ſubſtance / vſyng the ſame reaſon that maſter haddon dyd be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore him / and whan he hadd receyued the ſame anſwer alſo that was made to maſter haddon / he ſayd it was but a lewde refuge / whan they could not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer / to denye the auctor. Yet he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd the auctor to be a catholyk doctor / and this proued / he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmid his ſaing (of the nature and ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) further: for the ſimilitude of theodorete is this / ꝙ he. As the tokins of chriſtes body and blood affter the inuocacion of the priſt
<pb facs="tcp:15046:28"/>
doo change theyr namys and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinewe the ſame ſubſtance / So the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of chriſt affter his aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyon / changed his name and was called immortall / yet had / it his former faſſhon / fygure and cyrcumſcripcyon / and to ſpeake at one word / the ſame ſubſtance off his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy. Therfor / ſayd maſter cheyny / yff in the former part of the ſimilitude / yow denye the ſame ſubſtance to continew / than in the latter part of the ſimilitude which agreth with it / I will denye the body of chriſt / affter his aſcenſyon to haue the former nature and ſubſtance: but that were a gret heriſy / therfor it is alſo a gret heriſy to take a way the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance of breade and wyne affter the ſanctificacyon. Than was maſter wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon enforcyd to ſay that the ſubſtance of the body in the former part of the ſimilitude brought in by him / dyd ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifye quantite and other accidencys of the ſacramentall tokens which be ſene / and not the very ſubſtance of the ſame. And therfor theodoret ſayth / (que vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur.) et ce, that is thos
<pb facs="tcp:15046:29"/>
thinges which be ſene for according to philoſophy / the accidentes of thingys be ſene / and not the ſubſtances.<note place="margin">M. cheny appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Than maſter cheyny appealed to the honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble menn and deſiered that they ſhuld gyue no credyte vnto them in ſo ſaing / for yff they ſhuld ſo thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ck / as thei wold teach / affter theyr lordſhyppys had rid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den xl. mylys on horſeback / as theyr beſynes doo ſometyme require / they ſhuld not be able to ſaye at night that thei ſawe theyr horſes all the day but only the color of theyr horſys / and by his reaſon chriſt muſt goo to ſtole and lerne of Ariſtotle to ſpeake. For whan he ſawe nathanaell vnder the figg tree yff Ariſtotle had ſtand by / he wold ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſayd / no chriſt / thow ſaweſt not him but the color of him / Affter this / wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon ſayd / what yff it were gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted that theodorete was on theyr ſide / where as they had one of that opinyon / there we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re an hundreth on the other ſyde.<note place="margin">morga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called for to help at a pinch.</note> Than the prolocutor called for maſter mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to help. And he ſayd that Theodo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rete did not more than he might lauful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lly doo. For firſt he granted the truth / 
<pb facs="tcp:15046:29"/>
and than / for feare of ſuch as were not fully inſtructed in the fayth / he ſpake (enigmaticos) that is couertly and in a miſteri / And this was lawfull for him to doo. For firſt he granted the truth and called them the body of chriſt and the blood off chriſt / than affterward he ſemed to gyue ſomewhat to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and to reaſon. but that theodoret was of the ſame mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that thei were of / the wordis folowyng quoth he / doo de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare. For that which foloweth is a cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe off that which went before / and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for he ſayth (The immortalyte &amp; ce.<note place="margin">morga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is taken with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ls allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the text</note>) whereby it doth appeare that he ment the dyuyne nature and not the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Than was morgan taken with miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alleagyng of the text. For the booke had not this word (for) for the greke word dyd rather ſignifye (truly / ) and not / (for / ) ſo that it myght manifeſtly appeare that it was the begynning of a newe matter and not a ſentence ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering a cauſe of that he had ſayd be ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. Than was it ſayd by watſon agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / ſuppoſe that theodorete be with yow / which is one that we neuer hard
<pb facs="tcp:15046:30"/>
off printed / but iij. or iiij. yearis agoo. Yet he is but one / And what is one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the hole conſent of the church. Affter thys maſter cheyny inferrid / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at not only theodorete was of that my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd / that the ſubſtance of breade a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne doo remayne / but diuers other alſo and ſpecially Ireneus / who makyng mencyon of this ſacrament / ſayth thus whan the cupp which is mingled with wyne / and the breade that is made / doo receyue the word of god / it is made the thankis gyuing of the body and blood of chryſt / by the which the ſubſtance of our fleſſh is noriſſhed and doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyſt. Yff the thankis geuing doo noriſſh our body / than there is ſome ſubſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes chriſtes body. To the which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / both watſon and morgan anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / that (ex quibus / ) by the which / in the ſentence of Ireneus were referred to the next antecedent / that is to the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and blood of chriſt / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not to the wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / which is in the cupp and the breede that is made. maſter cheiny replied th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at it was not the body of chriſt / which noriſſhed our bodyes. And let it be th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at
<pb facs="tcp:15046:30"/>
chriſtes fleſſh noriſſh to immortalite yet it doth not anſwer that argument / although it be trewe / no more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that anſwere which was made to my alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacyon owt of. ſ. Paull / The breade which we breake et ce. with certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other like / whereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to yow anſwered that brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de was not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there in his ꝓper ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficacyon / but for that that it had bene: Nomore tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rodd of Aaron which was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / becaus it had bene a ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Affter this maſter cheny brought in hiſichius and vſed the ſame reaſon that he dyd of the cuſtome of burning of Symbolys / and he axed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what was burnt. Maſter watſon ſayd we muſt not inquyre nor axe / but yff there were any fawte / impute it to ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.<note place="margin">Harpſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led in to help watſon</note>
Than ſayd maſter cheiny / where of came thos aſſhys / not of a ſubſtance? or can any ſubſtance ryſe of accyden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce? Than was maſter harpyſfeld called led in / to ſee what he could ſay in the matter. who told a fayre tale of the omnipotency of god / and of the imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillitye a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d weakenes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / not able to atteyne to godly thinges. And he ſayd it was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient that what ſo
<pb facs="tcp:15046:31"/>
euer we ſawe / felt / ortaſted / not to truſt our ſenſys / And he told a tale owt of ſ.<note place="margin">here is goodly geare / as if it were<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owt of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend of lyes.</note> cypryane how a woman ſawe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament burnyng in hir cofer / and that which burnid there / quod harpyſfeld / burnyth here and becomyth aſſhhes. but what that was that burnt he could not tell. But maſter cheyny contyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed ſtyll and forced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion / what it was that was burnt? It was eyther / ſayd he / the ſubſtance of breade or els the ſubſtance of the body of chriſt / which were to moch abſurdy te to grant. At length they abſwered that it was a miracle:<note place="margin">weſton wold knowe wheth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thei were ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficientli anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he nor his had not an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered ond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> where at maſter cheyny ſmiled and ſayd that he could than / ſay no more. Than D. weſton ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the company there whether thos men were ſufficiently anſwered or not certen pryſtes cryed yea / but thei were not hard at all / for the great multitude which cryed No / No: which crye was hard and noyſed allmoſt to the end of powlys. Whereat D. Weſton beyng moch moued / anſwered bitterly that he axed not the iudgement of the rude multytude and vnlerned peple / but of
<pb facs="tcp:15046:31"/>
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which were of the hows. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ared he of maſter haddo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his felows whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther thei wold anſwer them other iij. dayes. Haddon / cheiny and elmer ſayd no. But the archdeacon of wincheſter ſtode vp a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſayd that thei ſhuld not ſay but they ſhuld be anſwered / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d though all other dyd refuſe to anſwer / yet he wolt not but offered to anſwer them all / one affter a nother:<note place="margin">mark meſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency.</note> with whos pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer the prolocutor was not contentid / but rayled on him and ſaid that he ſhu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ld goo to bedlem. To whom the arch-deacon ſoberly made this anſwer: that he was more worthy to be ſent thether who vſed him ſelff ſo ragingly in that diſputacyon with owt any indifferent-equalite.<note place="margin">a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of weſton, where he is not able to anſwer he wold owt fa-</note> Than roſe D. Weſton vp and ſayd / There hath all the company ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrybed to our article / ſauing only thes menn / which yow ſee What theyr rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are / yow haue hard. We haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweryd them iij. Dayes / op on promes (as it pleaſed him to deſcant / with owt truth / for no ſuch promes was made) that thei ſhuld anſwer vs agayne / as long: As the order of diſputacyon doth
<pb facs="tcp:15046:32"/>
require: and yff they be able to defend their doctrine / let them ſo doo. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter elmer ſtode vp a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ꝓued how a vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne a man weſton was: for he affyrmed that thei neuer promiſed to diſpute / but only to open and teſtifie to the world their conſcyences: for whan thei were required to ſubſcribe thei refuſed / and ſayd thei wold ſhewe good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich mouyd their conſciences that thei could not with their conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be / as thei had partly allredy done and were able to doo more ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for / quoth he / it hath bene yll called a diſputacyon / and thei worthy to be bla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>met that were the auctors of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. For we ment not to diſpute / nor now meane not to anſwer / before our argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis / quoth he / which we haue to propownd / be ſoluted according as it was appointed. For by anſweryng we ſhuld but incomber our ſeluys and profite nothing / ſins the matter is all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy decreyd vp on and determined / what ſo euer we ſhall proue or diſpute to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15046:32"/>On monday folowyng beyng the xxx. of october / <note place="margin">weſton</note> the prolocutor deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Iohn fyllpot archdecon of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter whether he wold anſwer in the queſtions before propowned / to th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir obieccyons or no? To whom he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de this anſwer that he wold willingly ſo doo / yff according to theyr former determinacyon / thei wold fyrſt anſwer ſufficiently to ſome of his argumentie as thei had promiſed to doo: whereoff he had a doſen and not halff of the firſt yet decyded: And yff thei wold anſwer fully and ſufficiently but to one of his argumentis / he promiſed that he wold anſwer all the obyeccyons that they ſhuld bring. Than the prolocutor bad hym propownd his argument and it ſhuld be reſolutely anſwered / by one of them / whereunto maſter morgan was appoynted.<note place="margin">fylpot a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan.</note> Vp on wede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſday laſt / quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th he / I was inforced to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before I had beaten owt halff of myne argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / the ſomme where of was this / as was gatheryd by the iuſt context of the ſcripture / that the humane body of
<pb facs="tcp:15046:33"/>
chriſt was aſcended into heauen and placyd on the right hand of god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / wherefor it cold not be ſituate vp on earth in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the altare inuiſible affter the Imaginacyon of man. The argument was denyed by morgane. For the profe whereoff / fyll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot ſayd that this was it that he had to confirme his firſt argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / yff he my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght haue bene fufferid the other daye: as thus. One ſelfe and ſame nature / ꝙ he / receiuith not in it ſelff any thing th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at is contrary to yt ſelfe / but the body of chriſt is an humane nature diſtinct from the deitye / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is a proper nature of yt ſelff / ergo / it can not receyue any thing that is contrary to that nature and that varieth from it ſelfe but bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyly to be preſent and bodyly to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent / to be one earth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be in heauyn and all at one preſent tyme / be thinges contrary to the nature of an humane body / ergo it can not be ſayd of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane body of chriſt / that the ſelff ſame body is both in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and alſo in earth at one inſtant / either viſybly or inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Morgan denyed the maior / that
<pb facs="tcp:15046:33"/>
is the firſt part of the argument. The which fylpot vowched owt of vigilius an awneyent wryter.<note place="margin">here is a newe euaſion inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who dareth not plai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vigi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lius auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toritye / but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lor.</note> But morgan ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilled / that it was no ſcripture and bad him proue the ſame owt of ſcrypture. Filpot ſaid he could alſo ſoo doo / and right well diduce the ſame owt of. ſ. Paul / who ſayth that chryſt is like vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs in all pointes / except ſynne / and therefor / like as one of our bodyes can not receyue in it ſelff any thing contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to the nature of a body as to be in paulis church and at weſtminſter at one inſtant or to be at london viſibly / and at lyncoln inuiſibly at one tyme. for that is ſo contrary to the nature of a body and of all creaturys that as dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d baſilius doo affyrme / that an inuiſyble creature / as an angell / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be at one tyme in diuers placis: where for he concluded / that the body of ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt might not be in moo places than in one / which is in heauin and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently / not to be conteyned in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the altare. To this the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutor toke vp on him to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer / ſaing that it was not trew that chriſt was ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:15046:34"/>
vnto vs in all pointes / as fylpot to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke yt / except ſynn:<note place="margin">weſton. anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth / wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſely / I warant yow / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pythily</note> For that chriſt was not conceyued by the ſede of man as we be. To the which fylpot replied that chriſtes concepcyon was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed before by the angell / to be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall / but after he had receiued our nature / by the operacion of the holy gooſt in the virgins womb / he became affterwardes in all pointes like vnto vs except ſynn.<note place="margin">morga-</note> Than morgan inferred that this ſaing of paul dyd not playne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly proue his purpoſe. Well quoth fyll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot / I perceyue yow doo anſwer but by cauillacion: Yet am I not deſtitute of other ſcriptures to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme my firſt argument / allthough yow refuſe the probacion of ſo awncient and catholy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a doctor as vigilius is. S. Peter in the ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he made in the third of the actes / making mencion of chriſt / ſaith thes wordes / whom heauen muſt receyue / vntill the conſummacion of all thinges / et ce. Which wordes are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his humanitie. No wyff heauen muſt hold chriſt / than can he not be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re on earth in the ſacrament as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb facs="tcp:15046:34"/>
Than morga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / laughing at this and geuing no direct anſwer a tall / har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſfeld ſtode vp which is one of the biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of londons chaplins and toke vp on him to anſwer to the ſaing of. ſ. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / and demandid of filpot whether he wold neceſcitate / that is / of neceſſitye force / chriſt to any place or no? Fylpot ſayd that he wold no notherwiſe force chriſt of neceſſitie to any place / than he is taught by the wordes of the holy gooſt / which ſownd thus that chriſtes humane bodie muſt abyde in heauen vntill the daye of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / as I reher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed owt of the chapter before mencio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<note place="margin">harpſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld.</note>
Why / quoth harpiſfeld / doo yow not knowe that chriſt is god omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? Yes / ſayd fylpot / I knowe that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght well neyther dowt I any thyng at all of his omnipotency / but of chriſtes omnipotency what he may doo is not our queſtyon / but rather what he doth I knowe he may make a ſtone in the wall / a man / yff he lyſt / and alſo that he may make moo worldes / but doth he therfor ſoo?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15046:35"/>It were no good conſequent ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude / he may doo this or that / therfor he doth it. We muſt byleue ſo moch of his omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy / as he by his word ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th declared and taught vs: but by hys word he hath taught vs that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens muſt receyue his body vntill the daie of dome: therfor we ought ſo to bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue. Why / quoth the prolocutor / than yow wyll put chriſt in priſon in heauin To the which fylpot a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered doo yow reken heauen to be a pryſon?<note place="margin">weſton.</note> god gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs all to come to that priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Affter this harpiſfeld inferred that this word (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet) in.<note place="margin">the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutor and fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por.</note> ſ. peter which dyd ſignifie in Ingliſſh / (muſt / ) dyd not import ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch as I wold inferr of neceſſitye. as by other placis of ſcripture it may appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / where (oportet) is as well as there as in the firſt to timothy where paul ſaith / (oportet epiſcopum eſſe vnius vxoris virum / ) a biſſhop muſt be the huſband of one wife / here quoth he / (oportet / ) muſt. doth not import ſuch a neceſcytie but that he that neuer was maryed mai be a biſſhop. To this fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot ſaid againe that the placis were not
<pb facs="tcp:15046:35"/>
like which he went abowt to compare. which thing ought ſpecially to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in conferring of wordis / or ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures to gether. For that in the place bi him alleaged. ſ. paull doth declare of what qualitye a biſſhop ought to be. but in the other. ſ. peter teacheth vs the place where chriſt muſt neceſſarily be vntyll the end of the world / which we ought to bileue to be trewe. And this comparyſon of this word (oportet / ) doth no more anſwer myne argument than yff I wold ſay of yow / now being here (oportet te hic eſſe) yow muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis be here (which importeth ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitye for the tyme / that yow can no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe be but here) a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yet yow wold goo abowt in wordis to auoyde thys neceſſitye with a nother (oportet) or a nother / (muſt / ) in a nother ſentence as this / (oportet te eſſe viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonum) yow muſt be a good man. where (oportet) doth not in very dede conclude ani ſuch neceſſitie but that yow may be an yll man. Thus yow may ſee that your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is not ſufficyent / and as it were no anſwer to my argument. Than the
<pb facs="tcp:15046:36"/>
prolocutor brought in a nother (opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet) to help this matter yff it myght be ſayng / what ſay yow to this (oportet hereſes eſſe / ) muſt heriſyes nedis be therfor bicaus of this word (oportet?) no truly / quoth fylpot / it can not other wyſe be / yff yow will add that which foloweth immediately vp on thos wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis of paul / that is (vt qui electi ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtentur) that is / that ſuch as be the elect of god may be manifeſted a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen. Why / quoth the prolocutor / the tyme hath bene that no hereſyes were. I knowe no ſuch tyme / quoth fillpott / for ſyns the time of Abell and Cayn heriſies haue bene and than begann thei. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd the prolocutor / wil yow now anſwer morgan an argument s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>? I will / quoth fyllpott / yff I may firſt be anſwered of myne argument any thing according to truth and to lerning What / quoth the prolocutor / yow will neuer be anſwered. How I am anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / quoth fyllpott / let all men that are here preſent iudge: and ſpecially ſuch as be lerned / and with what cauilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons yow haue dalyed with me. Firſt
<pb facs="tcp:15046:36"/>
to the awncyent auctoritye of vigilius yow haue anſwered nothing at all / but only denieng it to be ſcripture that he ſaith. Secondarily tot he ſaing of ſ. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the actis ye haue anſwered thus / demanding of me / whether I wold ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe chriſt in priſon or no. Let all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now iudge yff this be a ſufficient anſwer or no. Than ſtode morgan vp agayn / and axed filpott whether he wold be ruled by the vniuerſall church or no?<note place="margin">Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</note> Yes / quoth he / yff it be the trewe catholike church. And fith yow ſpeake ſo moch of the church I wold fayne that yow wold declare what the church is.<note place="margin">The church.</note> The church / quoth morhan / is diffuſed and diſperſed through owt the hole world. That is a diffuſe diffinicion / quoth fyllpot / for I am yet as vncerten as I was before what yow meane by the church. But I knowlege no church but that which is grownded and fownded on gods word as S. Paull ſaith / vp on the fowndacyon of the prophetis and apoſtles / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on on the ſcripturys off god. What / quoth moreman / was the ſcripture before the church? Yea
<pb facs="tcp:15046:37"/>
quoth fylpot / <note place="margin">More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and fylpot.</note> But I will proue Nay / quoth moreman / and I will beginne at chriſtis tyme. The church of chriſt was before any ſcripture writton. For Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thewe was the fyrſt that wrote the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell abowt a doſen yearys affter chriſt ergo the church was before the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. To whom filpot anſweryng / denied his argument. Which whan morema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cowld not ꝓue / filpot ſhewed that his argument was (elechus) or a fallace / that is a deceyuable argument. For he toke the ſcripture onli to be that which is wrytton by men in letters / where as in very dede all prophecy vtteryd by the ſpiryte of god / was cownted to be ſcripture before it was wrytton in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Inck. For that it was wrytto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the hartis and grauen in the mindis yea and inſpyred in the mowthys of good men and off chriſtis apoſtles by the ſpirite of chriſt: As the ſalutacion of the Angell was the ſcripture of ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt and the word of god before it was wryton. At that moreman cryed / fye / fye: wondring that the ſcripture of god ſhuld be cownted ſcrypture before it
<pb facs="tcp:15046:37"/>
was writton / and affirmed that he had no knowlege that ſo ſayd. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot anſwerid that concerning knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in this behalff / for the triall of the truth abowt the queſtions in controuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſy / he wold wyſſh hym ſelff no worſe matched than with moreman. At the which ſaing / the prolocutor was gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſly offended / ſaing that it was arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him / that wold compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re with ſuch a worſhipfull lerned man as morema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was / being him ſelff a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnlerned / yea a mad man meter to be ſent to bedlem than to be a mong ſuch a ſort of lernyd and graue men as the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re were / and a man that neuer wold be anſwered / and that trobled the whole hows: And therefor he dyd command hym that he ſhuld come no more in to the hows demanding of the hows whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther thei wold agree thereupon or no. To whom a gret no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber anſwered Yea. Than ſayd fylpot agayne that he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght thinck him ſelff happy that was owt of that company. Affter this mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan roſe vp and rownded the prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the eare. And than agayne the
<pb facs="tcp:15046:38"/>
prolocutor ſpake to fylpott and ſayd / leſt yow ſhuld ſlander the howſe and ſay that we wyll not ſuffer yow to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare your mind we are content / yow ſhall come in to the hows as yow haue done before / ſo that yow be apparelyd with a long gown and a typpet as we be / and that yow ſhall not ſpeake but whan I comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yow. Than quoth fylpot / I had rather be abſent alltogether. And thus thei ended.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>All glory to god only.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at Baſil by Alexander Edmonds.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Faultes eſtaped in the printing. In the ſecond ſyde of the ſyxt leaffe of the letter B. affter thes words (as thei imagin it to be / or no) reade thus. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd yea. Than ſayd M. dea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15046:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
